[music]
Welcome to the course digital
transformation and technological
innovation. So as we talked about in the
last session this is uh being introduced
as a core course for information systems
discipline and in the last session we
were talking about some of the
directions for innovation information
system research. So let's uh you know
continue with that. So we talked about
the human angle uh in the last part of
previous session. Now let's continue
directions for innovation information
systems. Now if we take another angle
which is the information angle right. So
another line of research that typically
you know is researchers they undertake
is that using different information or
providing information in different form
or level of detail. So because you know
most the information system they have a
machine element there is an input and
there would be a processing and then
there would be output. So everything is
relying on data. So can we work on the
data? Can we improve it? Can we take
different information uh from you know
maybe by changing the source or maybe we
can provide additional information or
maybe you know different form
presentation of the information we can
do for example if we are talking about
the AI system like we do feature
engineering right so similarly we can uh
you know look at from you know different
uh information perspective and we can
look at the level of detail kind of
detail that was uh that was being being
used by the information system right so
this is another angle for innovation or
research information systems then next
one is the uh technology angle so in the
technology angle we are directly
focusing on the you know the technology
subsystem of it or the machine uh
element of information system where we
can look at reconfiguring the system
whether reconfiguration or different uh
aspects of it whether that can help
improve the system the current state of
it and then We can always talk about the
upgrading as we talked about most of the
software products there would be a you
know new version that will be keep
coming that will come up just like we
see in our you know operating systems
that we install in our machines right
every you know few days there would be
an update to it. So very similar thing
we are talking about here whatever
machine component that we have it might
get an upgrade. So to be able to work on
that upgrade that becomes uh you know
what kind of upgrade can be there what
kind of a changes improvement bug fixes
and other aspects software engineering
aspects or the program design
architecture aspects uh can be can be
improved. So that also can be another
angle for innovations upgrading and then
replacing technologies right. So some of
the components within the machine that
might be useful earlier but but now with
the advent of you know uh new technology
you know we can replace that for example
instead of using you know the keyboard
or instead of using our mouse computer
mouse for interaction or for clicking we
can you know use touch screen. So that
is a replacing the way input is being uh
you know given to a particular you know
computer right. So similarly we can look
at you know different element uh of the
you know you know technology which can
be replaced because something new
something better has come up and that
can be incorporated and therefore
overall information systems can be
changed. So these are you know another
you know set of angles that can be
undertaken for innovation and research.
Then what are the benefits of
information systems? Now data
information passing that is undertaken
uh information system that can create
feedback mechanisms for decision making.
So this feedback mechanism in in in the
sense you know people who are
interacting with the system they'll tell
what is working what is not working or
in what scenario the output was not
acceptable whether and you know where is
the issue maybe the machine maybe the
input maybe human error maybe the
process is not right. So different
element of information system can be
looked at you know but where that is
coming from you know that is feedback
mechanism. So people interacting and
therefore uh that can be looked at to
actually benefit right. So data
information processing the data the logs
that are there that can be used to
create you know feedbacks and therefore
you know we can improve the system and
you know the insights that we generate
from information systems right the
output that we generate from information
systems that will directly go into the
decision making of the you know the
manager or you know any decision maker
or the business organization. Then what?
So what are other generic benefit of
information system? So that is speed and
accuracy. So whatever you are doing
manually or through a paperbased system
if you use information systems where the
machine the algorithms and the
interaction the process and everything
is very well defined. So that can
improve the speed and accuracy and
therefore the productivity and
efficiency benefits are there. And
because of the productivity and
efficiency benefits there can be
increased revenues, there can be reduced
cost and overall effect of all this can
be that some of the organizational goals
for example increasing profits,
improving customer service those can be
achieved. So overall what we are trying
to suggest here is the benefits of
information systems they go all the way
to meeting organizational goals which
are increasing profits and improving
customer service. But how things start?
We start at the you know data
information and we generate the feedback
mechanism for the system itself and then
for decision making uh so that you know
we keep on improving on in terms of
insights of the output that are getting
generated through those systems. We
improve on the speed and accuracy and
therefore the productivity efficiency
the generic benefits of you know having
information systems they also help in a
long way. Now moving on to uh set the
context here why you know information
systems are so important and we see them
everywhere in our professional and
personal all walks of you know life. So
because we are into an era of
information economy everything is being
driven by data information through apps
through internet through different
systems that we interact with for every
little thing that we do right. So basis
of all this is information. Now if we
look at the information economy the main
value is coming from the way we are
working with the information. So the
information while it's helping with the
overall process outputs inputs and
everything it in itself it has some
value right that so in itself you know
when we talk about a particular fact for
example what was the improvement in
sales in the last quarter. So that small
piece of information that sales growth
in the last quarter that information
itself has a value because if we have
that information as a manager we might
be willing to act on it. We might be
willing to make certain improvements or
willing to do more focus on production
or some sales aspect or the marketing
aspect or the production operations
aspect. Right? So that simple
information that sales growth you know
was less than previous quarter or more
than you know previous quarter that
itself has a value. So that is the point
information itself has value and uh
commerce that we typically do that
involves more often than not in the
information economy some exchange of
information right so even if you are
simply doing a financial transaction
that transaction you know from which
account to senders account to
receivers's account all that detail the
amount that is being transferred and the
time stamp that goes with it and you
know maybe the app that you were using
it you know all that right so there's so
much of exchange of information that
inherently happens uh in case of you
know information economy right so the
exchange of information is there and the
information itself has a value and then
impact we have already talked about
right the overall the impact of
information systems and the benefits of
information systems so all this put
together is actually defining the era of
you know information econom economy. Now
moving on now digital online or
electronic mode you know these are the
digital online electronics you terms you
know being used interchangeably quite
often nowadays so what they enable so
you know few examples are here for
example you know investment decision
involving large amounts so if you didn't
have the digital means uh the digital
online electronic means the information
systems that we get to look at our
stocks we log into our system the
accounts that we have from banks, demat
accounts, bank accounts and other things
because we have access to some of our
accounts and the stock information and
all that. We are able to we are not
relying on the manual process or the
physical process of getting the you know
cash or amount to be able to buy a
particular stock right. So all that is
taken away. the constraints of the
physical world are taken away and if we
have the amount with us in the bank we
can make that investment decisions. So
any large amount also we can make
investment decisions but in when we face
the physical in you know constraints we
cannot carry that uh you know large
amount of cash from one place to
another. So obviously people used to
carry and there were challenges and risk
and other things that were there but now
when we are in the information economy
when we are in the digital online
electronic mode so those constraint
those physical constraint of carrying
cash are taken away. So if in case you
are making a large investment decision
that is immediately feasible because of
the systems that are there in terms of
you know payments connection to the
banks connection to the your you know
you know DMAT account and other things
huge volume of financial transaction now
because it has become so easy to make
financial transactions for example all
of us we use UPI apps and there is no
transaction fee if you compare this with
a credit card or the net banking options
you see that there is a clear
transaction fee that is there. So what
has happened because of that huge number
of transactions are happening across the
income segments of uh you know our
country. So huge volume of financial
transactions are happening. So why this
is possible? Because you know digital
online electronic mode and all this
defines the magic of or the era of
information economy. Then if we look at
the you know if we want to order you
know supplies or you know distribution
of goods so that is also faster because
as we talked about in our examples of
information systems we talked about the
e-commerce websites the Amazon flip card
for food
swiggy for delivery you know blinket and
you know instamats and all that so even
at the personal or professional level
also the faster ordering is happening
same is applicable in For industries
also there are portals for the
industries. In case of government
organization there is a government e
marketplace jam. So faster ordering of
supplies, distribution of goods that is
feasible because of the digital online
and electronic mode. So all these
aspects these three important points
define you know the information economy
era that uh you know I talked about. Now
information as such is a central concept
in information systems right. So we
talked about earlier that information
itself it has its own value and then the
impact that it creates all around uh
through information system. So that is
already there but on its own it's has a
value. So information is one of the most
valuable resources for an organization.
Right now where the information is
coming from information coming from
data. So what how do we you know define
data? So data consists of recorded raw
facts right? So if we are you know going
to a retail store we are buying a set of
items. So all those items are part of
our transactions with the retail store.
So that gets recorded right so in the
transaction processing systems. So data
consist of recorded raw facts the set of
items that we bought from a retail
store. So that will be recorded here.
And so data consists of recorded raw
facts representing real world things. So
the items that actual purchase that we
do as a consumer from a retail store
that is a real world you know uh
activity that is happening. So few
examples employee ID for example within
an organization total hours worked in a
week you know for you know your paycheck
that information that data point will be
used to generate your paycheck your pay
slip inventory part number if you're
managing inventory. Okay. So that is
also you know a data point you know
which a particular inventory part
inventory item that is that is likely to
see stock out right. So that data is
important in that sense number of units
produced patient medical records. So few
examples I have given for you know
different context uh organization
context mainly. So essentially all these
examples uh you know signify what data
is about. recorded raw facts
representing real world things. So this
definition of data is mainly in the
information systems context right so
we're talking about the real world
things and real transactions that is
happening that being recorded as a you
know data point then moving on we want
to define information so many times
people are confused with what is data
and what is information so data we
already define that uh you know recorded
raw fact which represents a real you
know uh you know thing and the
information now so how it is different
we'll see information is a collection of
data organized and processed so some
sort of organization and processing is
happening so that means data is being
given a new representation some
organization some processing is
happening so information is collection
of data organized and processed so that
it has additional value right so simply
saying that your employee ID is this or
number of hours that you worked in this
week is this that is just a data point
right. So when we talk about information
so we do some organization so we uh you
know when we do that organization the
additional value comes for example how
many hours you worked in the month and
therefore given those number of hours
and given per day uh you know uh payment
this is your pay lift for the month
right so therefore that additional value
comes so when we uh place all the hours
that are there day you know for every
day or for every week we you know list
out all the hours of work. Then
essentially the summary gives us the
information in terms of what is the kind
of payment or paycheck is going to be
there at the end of the month for that
employee. Right? So that additional
value is coming because we are able to
present list out all the hours for
different days or weeks. So that
representation that organization or that
processing is creating additional
values. Therefore data in terms of
number of hours worked that is now when
presented for so many days uh you know
organized for so many days and or weeks
then that becomes information it brings
in additional value. So summarizing
similarly another example summarizing
individual sales data to see total sales
right. So a manager might be more
interested in seeing uh the total sales
for the for the month. So a manager uh
would be more interested in seeing uh
you know total sales for a month rather
than looking at individual sales data
point for different days or the weeks
right so that you know when you look at
for the months okay you can compare with
what happened in the previous month
right so therefore this presentation of
the data you know sales on different
days and then total summary of it the
summarization of it or the organization
and passing of it which gives us the
idea that okay in a month what happened
that be that brings in additional value
so that becomes information. So there is
some additional value which is coming uh
because of organizing or processing data
and when that you know that value is
there then we say we arrive at
information. So that being a difference
between data and information that
information brings in additional value.
You can act on information. You can only
display the data, right? But you can act
on information. So therefore, because
the information has an additional value.
Then moving on, exchange of information.
So exchange of information stimulates
activity and leads to better value
creation. Right? So simple exchange day
in day out for many people day in day
out. For some people, you know, once in
a while you will see messages uh coming
from retail stores and other websites
that you have created account or given
your mobile numbers to create account.
They will be sending you the discount
information and they'll they'll be
giving you the details about you know
the sales and that is happening or the
discount offers that are running or the
festival uh sale or some other seasonal
sale that is happening. So that simple
message that exchange of information
that there is a discount offering that
is running for few days or for given
dates that can you know stimulate
activity. What activity in this case?
Because discount we are talking about
the discount uh offers uh discount
message going to customers. So people
might visit those stores, people might
log into those websites and therefore
simple exchange of information might
stimulate activity. So therefore you
know this additional value you know this
additional value is coming because the
exchange is happening. So information
because it is organized and processed so
it will create additional value and then
because of the exchange that happens
then further value is created because it
will stimulate some activity. Right? So
let's move on. Now next step is analysis
of information. Right? So in analysis of
information integrated from different
sources. Now when we talk about the
sales data or you know number of hours
per employee you know this is you know
coming from maybe the source within the
uh organization. But if you are doing
some analysis for you know some uh you
know organization level decision making
then you might be interested in knowing
about the economy how the market is
going how the interest rates are going
how the oil prices are going and all
those aspects. You might want to
incorporate some of the happenings that
are h that are that are that are
happening in your immediate environment
or in the economy or in the industry or
the economy in general or worldwide.
some of that information might be
important for your analysis, right? So
you might have to you might be willing
to integrate you know information from
different sources so that you can
generate better insights and then
maximize desirable business outcomes
right the market demand is likely to go
up because you know some of the demand
that was uh being catered by some other
country that is not happening because
let's say war is happening or you know
some other scenario or crisis or has
happened and because of that that demand
that demand that demand that was being
served by one country might come to your
country and therefore part of that might
come to you as an organization. So
therefore you know if that uh you know
source that information if you can
quantize it if you can you know measure
it then accordingly you can you know see
what tiny part of that demand you can
cater to right so that analysis is
needed right so matching relevant
content to customers this is another
example matching relevant content to
customers interest based on email
marketing campaign data so this is
another source So whatever data that you
have from your transaction processing
systems that is there that you can
analyze and you can understand how the
customer which come to your website or
is you know your your store how they
behave how they make their purchases
other other interactions other
transactions. But you can also do some
something like this email marketing
campaign and that data can give you
additional inputs and you can integrate
that data also with your existing data
and therefore you can analyze that and
uh you can match uh you know some of uh
the customer some of the interest of the
customers which were not earlier being
catered to. So therefore this can
produce additional this might produce
additional sales because of this uh you
know campaign data that is there. So
analysis when we incorporate or
integrate you know uh you know data or
information from different sources that
can also help us uh generate new
insights and therefore uh help us
maximize our desirable business
outcomes. So the next is we already
touched upon this but few more uh you
know pointers on this how does data
become information right. So you know
data points arranged following a
specific defined relationship. So now we
are coming to you know the way to do it
right. So data points arranged following
a specific defined relationship enable
the emergence of a valuable piece of
information. Right? So arrangement we
talked about we can organize and process
data and there would be additional value
and that value differentiate information
from data. So that point is now being
elaborated upon that we need to define a
relationship between data points and use
that relationship to arrange the data.
Right? Adding similarly adding new or
different data can allow us to redefine
a relationship. So in light of new data,
in light of different data, whatever
relationship that we were earlier seeing
for our data points that can be
redefined and therefore a new
information can be created and then it
might be possible for us to act on that
new information because of the redefined
relationship between data points because
of the addition of new data. Right? So
then we can act on it and therefore it
can lead us to desirable business
outcomes. So for example adding product
data to sales data. So earlier we were
talking about the examples you know
sales data you know day- wise data and
you know we organize it you know in that
way organization of sales data and then
we get a uh insight on what is the
monthly sales like right similarly we
can add product data to that sales data
and now what we can get is we can get
sales information organized by product
right so we can analyze which product
line is doing better and which product
line is not doing so well. So when we
add one more piece of you know
information which is uh you know product
data right in along with the sales data
then additional insight seems to be
coming from that. Now we have more
information in terms of which product
line is doing well or not. So therefore
uh the focus of the managers and the uh
you know other executive executives can
sift to uh the underperforming
uh you know product line right moving on
perform data processing right so how to
transform data to information right few
pointers we talked about right now a few
more things so what we do in data
processing the process of you know
defining relationship among data points
to create useful information that is
referred as you know data processing
right so when we have defined the
relation you know shapes and we then act
on it then we'll have to process the
data so that we are able to arrive at
the you know useful information that we
wanted for so this you know this whole
step is referred to as data processing
and here what do we mean by process a
set of logically related tasks performed
to achieve a defined outcome right so
the defined relationship that we wanted
to exploit right we follow a set of
steps to process our data so that we can
arrive at the useful information. So you
know that overall uh you know data
processing will lead us again to you
know lead us help us to transform our
data into some meaningful information.
Now how do we know the relationships
that are hidden information? Until now
we talked about okay you know data
points and you organize them you arrange
them additional value information right
and other aspects also we talked about
then we also talked about that you know
the relationships uh we transform based
on the relationship now but how do we
know what relationships so what are the
relationship that might work so how to
know relationship hen information so
that is linked to the knowledge of the
problem domain domain. So we are working
in a e-commerce domain. So we need to
have the knowledge of e-commerce itself.
How different platforms they engage with
different sites of the e-commerce
platform, the buyers, the sellers, uh
you know the interactions, different
product categories that are there, the
review comments that come that act like
a feedback loop, right? So we need to
have the overall knowledge of you know
that particular domain and that
knowledge will give you the pointers as
to what relationships might be hidden or
underexplored and therefore we can you
know take advantage of that. So
knowledge is key here knowledge of the
problem domain. So knowledge
understanding of relationship in a set
of information and how to make that
information useful for decision making
or performing a specific task. So we got
to use our you know domain knowledge to
see what kind of rel relationships are
typically there and what is explored
what is not explored and you know that's
where we get you know our pointers in
terms of uh you know what to experiment
with what to try for for decision making
or for you know performing the task
itself. So information in sum in summary
to summarize you know what we have been
discussing till now information is data
made more useful through the application
of knowledge. Now we have incorporated
all these three elements the information
the data and the knowledge put together
in one sentence creating a gist out of
it. Information is data made more useful
through the application of knowledge.
When you apply the knowledge, you know
what relationships are underexplored and
therefore you use those relationship to
work on data to arrange it in such a way
that you get an information which is
more useful. Right? So information is
data made more useful through the
application of knowledge. So I hope the
difference between the data information
and the knowledge is clear because this
is very crucial in the information
systems discipline. Right. Now moving on
to data again. So data is stored,
organized and manipulated using database
systems. So we will talking about data
system in a more details later. But
while we have been talking about you
know organizing and processing data but
data needs to be stored somewhere so
that we can interact with it and you
know organize or manipulate it,
manipulate it. So that is uh you know
done through database systems. So we
have a figure here. So let's look at
this. So you can see you know collect
and select data maybe from sensor maybe
from lock files and all this raw data is
coming in here and then you create your
you know you know you organize your data
through your servers machines and here
is a representation in terms of tabular
layout. You can see row a column 1, row
B column 2, row A column 3 and all that
and multiple rows in in this three
columns in this right and then here you
can see you know the analysis part and
then process and manipulate data. So you
maybe look at uh you know few you know
measures, few metrics and you know some
you know summarization some averaging
counting. So all these will give us new
information about this data. So these
are the analysis points or summarization
points or we are working on the data
organizing or processing in such a way
that they will provide us some useful
information here. So what is the you
know transformation of data? So
transformation of data into useful and
valuable results is considered more
important than the sources and
processing of data. Right? So processing
and sources you know so that is there of
course that is important but how do we
transform data you know and what we make
out of it because data is to be you know
organized and processed or transformed
such a way that we are able to arrive at
useful information. So that
transformation part is considered more
valuable uh in in in information systems
in general you know than you know the uh
the source of it or the processing of it
uh on its own right because the
transformation will lead us to important
information that we can act on it and
therefore we can reach to our desirable
business outcome and therefore the
transformation is considered or given
more value. Right? Because it is
directly connected to the value of
information. Now what is value of
information? So how information helps in
decision making to achieve the
organization's goals and perform task
more efficiently and effectively. So
value of information depends on what is
stated in this that information should
be able to help in decision making. So
you know whenever you know we work with
information systems
you know inputs the processing the
activities the task and then the output
right so whether the output whether the
information you know is leading to uh
some insights some decision making that
is improving our output or enriching our
input or processing is simpler you know
better right faster or speedier some
element of it. So you know you know when
information you know touches some
element of it then it creates value
right and overall uh the system becomes
you know because overall system becomes
efficient effective and we are able to
reach to our desirable organizational
goals right so value of information is
linked to this whole you know process
now value of information is linked to
its data also so as we typically say
garbage in garbage out. So the data is
the starting point. So obviously you
know we are doing our own organization
processing analysis you know machine
element is also there the kind of
processing and the task that would be
run on it right that is also there but
essentially you know the value of
information is you know at a fundamental
level is linked to its data. So data
related issues can undermine the value
of information. So if the you know
garbage in garbage out the typical
saying that holds here right so we need
to work on you know data quality so
there are issues with the you know data
quality so that can undermine the value
of information. So in this session what
we have talked about we completed the
remaining part of you know research and
innovation angles that are typically
undertaken in information systems
domain. Then we also you know talked
about various t various aspects like how
data is uh you know transform into
information how the value is coming from
what are the relationships between data
points and then how to exploit those
relationship how to use knowledge you
know some of those angles we talked
about apply knowledge you know to
understand relationship then transform
you know those data points and arrive at
useful information then act on those
information to reach to desirable
outcomes. We also talked about value of
information and all those aspects. So
let's stop here and we'll continue our
discussion in the next session. Thank
you.
>> [music]
[music]